Before we move away from
static modeling with UML next week
and move into Petri nets
and thus dynamic modeling, I would
like to first introduce,
or I hope repeat for
most of you, some
mathematical tools/terms in this video.
So that would
be simple set theory
terms, specifically sets,
functions, and graphs.
Hopefully this will really just be
a review for many of you, in
particular the Komedia students
will recognize the slides
as they are quite similar to
my Mathematical Structures lecture after all.
I think also
for the computer science
students some of the slides will
be quite similar to the logic lecture.
And also for
the ISE students
these terms should be known,
for example from Discrete Mathematics.
Nevertheless, I repeat, simply so that
you also see the notation exactly
as I will have
it in the further slides.
Of course, if you find
that you already know all
of this, you
may skip this video.
We're going to
be dealing with sets.
So sets will occur in
the formalization of Petri nets.
And sets you know at least
from school as simply such collections of
elements, written
with braces.
If the sets can
be enumerated, piece by
piece, then it is
written down with commas.
And maybe dot, dot, dot,
if it's an infinite set
that can be continued
in a natural way.
Of course, there are also quantities that
cannot be written down in this way.
For example, you can't write down
the real numbers in exactly this way.
What one also likes to
do is to indicate sets by
describing their properties,
so to speak.
So, for example, the
set of all natural numbers
that are even, one likes to
write in this so-called comprehension notation.
So the set of
all n, "so that".
Then in this case
there is a condition.
Let the n come from
the natural numbers and be even.
With N written in
this way, we denote
the set of natural numbers
which also contains the zero.
In our specification of the vector operations,
or even before the vector operations in
the arithmetic operations, I had also
used this as a set briefly.
That would be again the representation for
some general property that depends on an x.
And if there is a basic set,
as it was the case here above, one
writes it gladly also in such a way
that one says already before the vertical line,
from which basic set the elements come,
which come into question for the set.
And then there
is another property.
That was "being even" above,
that can be any property.
With it
one means:
All elements from X, which
additionally satisfy the property E(x),
shall be gathered
in the set M.
This simply as possibilities
to write down sets.
Important for consideration of sets is,
that sets are unordered, and also
the number of elements, thus the
occurrence of an element, cannot be multiple.
First of all, sets are disordered,
so whether I write down \
or \ or any other
permutation of the numbers 1,2,3.
It is always
the same set.
Secondly, elements do not
appear more than once.
Or, if you would write them
down several times, it makes no difference.
The set \ is
still just the set \,
because it only matters if
an element is in the set:
Yes
or No?
And not somehow
how many times.
That means, these
sets are equal,
but of course different from \
and also from the set \.
Because there is actually one element too
much or too little in each case.
While this "double occurrence" of 4 is
just no indication for somehow "too much".
The 4 is
in the set.
So this distinguishes sets
from simply lists of elements.
Then there are
some notations and operations.
On the
one hand relations.
On the one
hand being contained.
So an element a is in
the set, if it occurs in it.
And this element sign
is the abbreviation for it.
Then we need sometimes for counting
the number of elements in a set.
Of course, this is only
possible if the set is finite.
Generally, sets can be
infinite, like the natural numbers.
But if this
is a finite set,
we use this notation here
to denote that finite number.
Then there is the notion of
subset and a corresponding symbol for it.
That is, A is
a subset of B.
Then every element from A
must also be contained in B.
This need not be true vice versa,
then the sets would even be equal.
But at least every element from
A must also be present in B.
So for example the even integer numbers
are a subset of all integer numbers.
That is, it works
for infinite sets too.
And it's not the same as
saying that the subset relation says
the sets are smaller in
the sense of "contain fewer elements".
It's really a matter of whether all the elements in A
are also in B, no matter how many there may be.
Then there is
this particular set.
It would have the
number of elements zero.
That's why you like to write
it with some kind of zero,
but as a set
zero with this crossbar.
Or just the curly
braces without anything in between.
So this is the
set that contains no elements.
It is automatically a subset, even
a real subset, of any other set.
Real subset in the sense that it is
not equal to any non-empty set, of course.
Then there are operations
which link several sets.
On the one hand there is
the set union, written with this symbol.
We will see the reverse symbol
for the average in a moment.
The union is
about throwing quantities together.
So the result set here is the set of all elements that occur
in A or in B. The result set cannot be smaller than this symbol.
The result set cannot be smaller
than either of the original sets.
And of course both A and B are
subsets of the union of A and B.
Then there is, so to speak, dual
to it, with the reverse symbol, the intersection.
That would be the set of all
elements that occur in A and in B.
So only the "or" in this
conditional has been replaced by "and".
But this makes
a big difference.
In particular, the average usually makes
sets smaller, at least not larger.
So the average of A and B is
in any case subset of both A and B.
While here the
reverse was true:
A and B are
each subset of the union.
These are operations on sets in such
a way that the kind of elements
that are in the result set would be
elements from the original sets A and/or B.
Then there is
another operation, the
so-called cross product
or "Cartesian product".
There the structure
of the elements changes.
So in the result set are other
kinds of elements than in the original set.
Namely not simply the elements from A
and/or from B, but pairs of them.
So we have given two sets A and
B, and we get the set of all pairs.
And ordered pairs in such a way,
that the first element, the left element
of the pair, always comes from the set A,
and the right element always comes from the set B.
Of course, the sets may
also be equal by chance.
But in the general case, these
are simply two sets A and B,
and the first element of the result pairs
always comes from A, the second from B.
For example, for a two-element
set and a three-element set,
the Cartesian product here
would be as follows:
That has
six elements.
It results exactly the number of elements of
a cross product with finite sets A and B
as the product of the numbers of
the elements of these two single sets.
Because we can pair every element from
this set with every element from that one.
There are exactly these
six pairs in the case.
Of course, the order in which we
write down the elements here doesn't matter.
So it is only about the fact that
these six pairs have to occur in the
result set, not in which
order we wrote them down here.
A special case would be the
Cartesian product with the empty set.
There always the
empty set comes out.
For example, no matter how large the
first set is, we cannot form pairs if
the second element, the
second component of the
pair, is to come from this
empty set (in which there is nothing).
This is what
I had just said:
For finite sets, the number of elements of
the cross product is equal to the number
product of the numbers
of the individual elements.
And you can also
think about certain relations
between the relations
we have seen.
For example, in the case of subset relation and the cross product, if
A is a subset of B, then the same kind of relation holds
even after cross producting with some set C. And it
doesn't matter if I have the set C or not.
And it doesn't matter whether I multiply the set C by it from the right
when I do the cross product, or whether I multiply it by it from the left.
These are simply compatibility properties of the
cross product, in that case with the subset
relation.
The important thing is that
the reverse is not true.
Just because this
subset relation holds
doesn't necessarily make this subset relation hold,
especially if C is the empty set.
That would be
to form pairs.
And just as you can form pairs
and form a cross product between two sets,
you can extend that
for more than two sets.
Then you get
triples, quadruples, quintuples, etc.
So we'll have
tuples at times in
the formalization that contain
more than two components.
And then the notation
is just quite analogous.
Then we write more than
two elements in such round brackets,
separated with
commas, the components.
From n components we form
n-tuples and for n = 3,
n = 4, n = 5
there are still special notations for them.
Of course, tuples are
not the same as sets.
So
really important:
Take round brackets here
and not curly brackets,
because the components here
are relevant in their order.
So while the set \ written
down and the set \ written
down, each written in
curly brackets, were the same
thing (this showed up a few
slides ago), it's just different for triples.
So the triple (1,2,3) is
really different from the triple (1,3,2),
although the
same elements appear.
But they appear
in a different order.
So as elements of this
triple cross product (cross product
between three sets) these are different
values, and this is very important here.
It is also true that an element
can appear several times in the tuple.
This is also different
from the situation with sets.
It's not that it doesn't matter
that the 4 is here twice.
These are really
different tuples, especially since
the one on the left is a quadruple
and the one on the right is a quintuple.
But also
independent of that.
If we were to write
4 and 4 here, for example,
that would also be significant,
that the 4 occurs twice.
Different
from sets.
Then there's another
construction on sets that
we'll need, called
the power set.
This starts from a single set, that is, not
two sets A and B, but a single set M.
And the power set
is the set A.
And the power set is the
set that contains all subsets of M.
This is written
with this calligraphic P.
So the power set of M
is a set consisting of sets,
and each contained set is
a subset from the original M.
It is called a power set
because the number of elements increases exponentially.
So approximately the power set of
the set \ is this eight-element set.
The set that consists of eight
elements, each of which is a set.
That is exactly all subsets
that exist of \, including the
empty subset and the entire
set as a subset of itself.
Then we can play games and consider
what this means for the empty set.
Then we find that the power set of
the empty set is just not the empty
set, but a one-element set
containing exactly the empty set.
This will rather not fall on
our feet here in the lecture,
because we will not
necessarily start from empty sets.
But it is important for
understanding ultimately also this power set
notion that it makes a difference whether I have the
empty set or the power set of the empty set.
You can iterate that, and then
more such exotic sets come out.
But they're
not absurd.
They simply follow from the
definition of the power set notion.
For finite sets, which is what they are
now in all three cases, this relation holds:
The number of elements of the power set is 2 to
the power of the number of elements of the basic set.
This is where the name power set comes
from, because this is a power of two.
And from this you can
see that if you form
power sets, for example in modeling
to capture states of a system,
there are then just
very quickly very many states.
That is one thing that one
would like to avoid, in modeling ultimately.
To repeat this notation, or just
to see it in action in
an example, let's take a look at
what such a state modeling might look like.
This is not yet an example of what I
would actually like to model dynamically directly as well.
For now, I just want
to use the terms we've seen
to describe the state
space of a possible system.
So let's say we want
to use a Petri net later
to model a
snack machine, for example.
That contains two kinds of snacks,
namely bars and chips, and of
course it can store a supply of
each of those two kinds to begin with.
In fact, in our
vending machine, it can
have a maximum of 30 pieces of
each of the two types in stock.
When you operate the vending machine,
you're dealing with a simple interface.
There is a yellow
and a red warning light.
One warning light indicates that there
is no change left in the machine.
And the other warning light means
that no more bills are accepted.
They can light up
independently of each other.
One could
also consider
that there could be a
logical connection between these two conditions.
But this should not be
assumed for the time being.
They can light up
independently of each other:
Neither of them
can light up, or
that the yellow one is on, or that the
red one is on, or that both are on.
What would be the set of
all possible states of this automaton?
What would you
have to remember in
each case, what could be all the
possible manifestations in which the automaton can be?
One can distinguish the states according to
which lamps are on or not on.
You can distinguish how many bars are
there and how many chips are there.
If one would enumerate
that, one could say:
One writes a
triple in each case.
In the first component, you
talk about which lights are on.
In the second, for example,
how many bars are present.
And in the third,
how many chips are present.
That would be
a triple cross product.
For these stock level indicators, you just
take a number between zero and 30.
Because those are the possible expressions, that you
have zero bars, two bars, up to 30 bars.
And what is the expression
for which lights are on?
That's
a subset.
It can be that no lights are on at all, the
yellow one is on, the red one is on, both are on.
That is, in the
first component of our state
triples we would want to store
a subset of the set \.
So our state space, the
set of all possible states of
this automaton, could be viewed as the
Cartesian product of the power set of the
set \ (which is
a set of two colors
simple) and in each of the other
two components a number between zero and 30.
So about the
element (empty set, 20,
10), which is undoubtedly an element of
this power set, would be interpreted like this:
This is the state in
which both warning lights are off
(because this is where the empty quantity is), and
there are still 20 bars and 10 packages of chips.
If one had seen both lights switched
on at the same stock level, then
one would simply have the full quantity \
in the first component instead of the empty quantity, which
is also a subset of this quantity, and
thus is an element of this power set.
Now one
can also ask:
How many
states are there?
Here
are two.
How many
are there altogether?
And there already the
state explosion would strike.
If one calculates by means of the
rules, which were further in front on the
slides, how one calculates the number
of elements of such a constructed set.
Because of the cross product, you would
get the multiplication of the number of these
elements, the number of these elements,
and the number of these elements.
And by the power set here, we have 2 to
the power of the number of elements in the inner set.
And then you would get a total
of something in the neighborhood of 4000:
4 times "more than
30" times "more than 30".
That's getting
close to 4000.
You don't want to just write
them all down as a graph.
And there we might have
to look for other ways,
especially to deal with
such stocks or resources.
That's where the high number
of possible triples comes from.
We will deal with that
later, how to model such things.
This means not only to specify
the quantity, but also to express
state transitions in
a compact way.
What we still need is
the notion of function or mapping.
Functions are
known from school.
So typical representatives, which one
uses in the analysis for example.
In the discussion of curves
we do something with functions.
But there is also
the general notion of
function for arbitrary sets and
not necessarily sets of numbers.
So
notation here:
The function has a name and maps
from a definition set to a value set.
And these are
just arbitrary sets:
Sets of numbers perhaps,
but conceivably also other sets.
For example, sets
that have occurred here.
So a pair of
elements, which are related.
For one, a possible
notation would be to
say, if we apply f to a,
b comes out, so b is f(a).
You know this from school, y
is f(x) for respective corresponding elements
from definition
and value domains.
We will write it
down partly like this, that
is, as an explicit mapping: a
is mapped to (or mapped to) b.
Then, if the set
A is finite, one could
simply make this kind of
specification for all elements from A.
This would describe
the function completely.
Of course, that doesn't work for functions like
the sine function, where we have the set
of all real numbers
here, to write down finitely.
But for many cases, especially when A
is finite, we can also describe a
function by finitely
many such mappings.
We can also use
the same kind of
notation when we specify a general mapping
rule, i.e., how a maps to f(a).
For example, "a squared" could also be specified
this way instead of by this y=f(x) notation.
Example:
The square function on the
set of integers, we would say
that is a mapping from
the integers to the natural numbers.
When we square, negative
numbers can't come out.
So even though you
can put negative numbers in
here, because of the set Z of
integers, a natural number always comes out.
One way to write down
the assignment rule is this equation:
f(z) is
z squared.
Or just by this
written down with this mapping
symbol, this information
represented in this way.
A few concrete pairs here would be just such
mappings as -3 to 9, -2 to four, etc.
In the concrete case, of course,
this cannot be written down finitely by
enumeration, because there are still infinitely many
negative and infinitely many more positive numbers.
But if the range were finite,
one could give a section here
and take that as a whole
as a description of the function.
That was the
notion of function.
And finally, we're
going to use graphs.
Of course, intuitively, we've done
that up to this point.
We've already had
graphs written down.
Formally, a graph is
also simply a set-theoretic construct.
So you have a
set of labels or labels.
Then a directed and edge labeled graph (these
will be the graphs we will be primarily interested
in) is given by a
node set and an edge set.
The edge set is
a subset of the
cross product of the node set with
the label set and with the node set.
That is, the edges will be triples in which
the first component is a node, the second component is
an element of the label set,
and the third component is another node.
With the interpretation that
it's an edge labeled
with that label from
the node to the node.
So now here are the sets, but
in the triple, these are concrete representatives:
a node, a
label, a node.
These abbreviations V and
E come from "vertices"
and "edges", the English
terms for nodes and edges.
These sets are
likely to be infinite.
We will often
deal with finite graphs.
But from the point of view of set theory, the
vertex and edge sets in particular can also be infinite.
The label set is then
usually a finite set after all.
It can also
be very small.
We can also have a
label set with only one element.
Then there is no
real information in it.
Then one would have formally always
this one element from the label set.
This corresponds basically
to an unlabeled graph.
The being directed comes from the fact
that we have triples here and not sets.
So there's a first
component and a last component.
You can interpret that as
a directed connection from this
node standing in the first component to
the node standing in the last component.
What about
empty sets?
I had
already discussed infinity.
What you can have is that the node set
is not empty, but the edge set is empty.
That would be a trivial graph where there
are only nodes and no edges between them.
What cannot be is that the node set
is empty but the edge set is not.
If L is empty, there can be no
edges, because that set would necessarily be empty too.
We had the
observation that some
set cross product with the empty
set is always the empty set.
So the normal cases are already
that we are dealing with non-empty sets.
Another
example:
Let's just take as a set of nodes
the representatives for farmer, wolf, goat, cabbage head.
Following up on our example
very early in the lecture.
And as the set of labels, we use
the relationships that came up in the example.
We had modeled static briefly, and there
we had talked about possession and feeding relationships.
And for this node set, this label
set, that would be a conceivable edge set.
That's a set of triples, where in each case the
first component comes from V, the second component comes from
L, and the third component comes from V.
And then, of course, we can represent that.
And of course, we can
also represent this pictorially as this
graph, which we had already
seen earlier in the lecture.
There were not these
letters F, W, Z, K,
but here the respective pictures for
farmer, wolf, goat, cabbage head were inserted.
We would then
really have pictures,
be it with photos in there or these
nodes with the respective labels from the set V.
But
importantly:
This one up
here is a graph.
This one below is
represented as an image somehow.
But mathematically, what's up
here is already a graph.
We don't have to translate this into
a picture to accept it as a graph.
It says up front here, a
graph is just such a pair of
vertex and edge
sets with this context.
So strictly speaking, these three
sets together are stated the graph.
And this below is simply
an image of the graph.
That's going to be relevant because we're just
going to represent Petri nets as graphs as well.
And then mathematically, it's not necessary to
paint that as a picture as well.
Instead, this mathematical representation
alone is an exact representation.
More about this in the next week,
when we will talk about Petri nets.